本字幕由诸神字幕组(kamigamiorg)制作仅供交流学习禁止用于任何商业用途
Give it to me!
寄越せぇ
日听：小伍King翻译：森罗小江校对：Syura时间轴：海底压制：Coolkid
All...
よしゃあ
...right!
They did it!
Well done!
よかた
That was no ordinary prefectural qualifier match.
県予選レベルの試合じゃねぇべ
I got goosebumps.
俺鳥肌立た
All right, time to line up!
よし整列だ
Right!
Now we're tied at one win and one loss.
これで一勝一敗だ
Don't get too cocky.
調子乗んじゃねぇぞ
乗れません
I won't.
Episode Twenty-five:
Declaration of War
Thank you for the match!
ありがとうございました
やたな先生
They did it, sir!
Yes.
It looked like...
あいつ
日向がどこに打てくるのかを読んだように見えた
he was actually able to predict
where Hinata was going to hit it.
ブロクに当たて軌道が変わてなければ
If the ball didn't hit the blockers and change trajectory,
That was a very heartwarming match.
見ていて本当に胸が熱くなる試合でした
he might've gotten it.
拾われていたかもしれない
Karasuno                Aoba Jousai
Nothing I say can change the results.
何を言おうとも結果は結果のまま
I can't lessen the bitterness you feel, either.
悔しさが薄まることもない
後悔の残るプレもあるだろう
I'm sure there are moments you regret.
With that in mind, let me just say something:
それでもまずは言わせてもらいたい
よく戦た
You fought well.
スタンドに挨拶に行こう
Let's go thank the people in the stands.
あれを決められずに
How can I be the ace when I couldn't even land that spike?!
何がエスだ
Thank you very much!
ありがとうございました
Hey, hurry up!
おい早く来いよ
Yeah!
倒れきた
We fell over!
調子乗りすぎだつの
You guys are way too worked up!
日向ボケェボケェ
Hinata, you moron! Moron!
普通に考えたらわかるだろうが
Isn't it obvious that was going to happen?!
Don't ever forget this sight.
よく目に焼き付けとくぞ
You goddamn moron!
We're definitely going to get our payback!
この借りは俺達が必ず返す
Yeah!
そろそろ行くて
Apparently we're about to head out.
Okay.
Kageyama!
影山
We're not gonna lose next time.
「次はぜてぇ負けねぇ」
Or so he says.
Yeah.
はいはいほらほら
Hey!
You guys were awesome!
すげぇぞお前ら
Yay!
Big Sis!
姐さん
Ryuu!
龍最後よく拾たなカコよかたぜ
I'm amazed you dug up that one spike at the end! You looked awesome!
Thanks...
You know, I'm really happy for all the support,
but could you please stop calling me by my first name?
つか応援は嬉しいんだけどよ
あんま名前で呼ぶなよなぁ
Don't be embarrassed!
照れんなこの
Ow, ow, ow!
おおすげぇぜ
That was a great serve, Tadashi!
いいサブだたぞ忠
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
The last one! The last spike was amazing!
最後の最後のスパイクすごかた
サンキュ
Thanks!
あざす
Thanks.
At the end, I couldn't help but remember our last match, so when I saw three blockers, it was quite chilling.
最後前回の記憶があたので
３枚ブロクに付かれた時は正直冷やとしましたが
Just like when Azumane faced the Iron Wall,
「鉄壁」を相手にした時の東峰と同じく
影山はこの先を考えて
Kageyama probably thought about the future and felt it best for Hinata to break through himself.
日向の手でブチ破らせることがベストだと思たのかもな
いや単に直感だたのかもしれないがな
Actually, it might've been nothing more than instinct.
It's so amazing that you got through such a tall block!
あんな高いブロク躱せるなんてすごすぎるよ
At the end, the Great King reacted to my movements.
最後大王様反応してた
I thought he was going to get it.
取られるかと思た
大王様やぱすごかたな
He really is amazing.
Can you load up the bus when it comes?
バス来たら荷物積んでくれる
I'm gonna go get everyone else.
まだ来てない奴ら呼んでくるから
Okay.
This is a warning, Oikawa.
忠告だ及川
もう道を間違えるな
Never take the wrong path again.
You took the wrong path.
お前は道を間違た
There was a place where you
could've realized your true potential.
もと力を発揮できる場所があたのに
But because of your worthless pride, you didn't choose it.
取るに足らないプライドのためにお前はそれを選ばなかた
So you're trying to tell me that I should've
gone to Shiratorizawa instead of Seijou, right?
それは青城じゃなくて白鳥沢に入るべきだたてことでＯＫ
No team is guaranteed to win.
成功が約束されたチムなんかないだろ
If nothing else, I can say...
少なくとも今ここでは
that my team is the best one here.
俺のいるチムが最強のチムだろうが
Wow, I see you're still laughably confident!
相変わらず面白いくらいの自信だな
Worthless pride, huh?
「取るに足らないプライド」
確かにね
That's true.
Listen up, Ushijima.
聞けよ牛島
俺は自分の選択が間違いだと思たことはないし
I've never once regretted my decision,
and my volleyball career isn't even close to over.
俺のバレは何ひとつ終わていない
取るに足らないこのプライド
Don't you ever forget
my worthless pride.
絶対に覚えておけよ
あそれとね
Oh, yeah.
If you keep focusing on me,
you'll get stabbed from where you least expect it.
俺ばか注視してると
思てもない方向からブスリ刺されるからね
What's that supposed to mean?
どういう意味だ
My junior...
俺の後輩
isn't smart, nor is he even close to my level yet...
頭悪いしまだぜんぜん俺に敵わないけど
それでも独りじゃなくなたあいつは強いよ
but now that he's no longer alone, he's dangerous.
カラスは群れで大きな白鷲さえ殺すかもね
A murder of crows might even be able to kill the great white eagle.
おい何やてんだ
Hey.
What the hell are you doing?
Hurry up and get your stuff onto the bus!
ささとバスに荷物積んじまえ
どうしたの二人とも
What's the matter?
痩せた土地で立派な実は実らない
Good fruit cannot be harvested from barren soil.
I'll show you just how much
we can grow from the concrete.
コンクリト育ちの力見せてやる
W-Wait!
待て
The Japanese National High School Boys' Volleyball Tournament Miyagi Prefecture Qualifier
Finals
Shiratorizawa
vs.
Karasuno
Shiratorizawa
vs.
Karasuno
!!
Haikyuu
Second Season
!!
Haikyuu
Second Season
They all passed out like we expected.
やはり爆睡ですね
Can't blame 'em.
無理もねぇわ強敵と２試合だもんよ
They played two hard matches today.
I really appreciate all you've done, sir.
先生には感謝してるよ
Where did that come from?
なんです突然
A team like ours who'd been struggling lately
うちみたいにしばらく何のツテもなかたチムが
got to play so many practice matches
with the powerhouse schools from Tokyo.
東京の強豪グルプと何度も練習試合できるなんて
All I can say is that we were blessed.
恵まれてるとしか言えない
You can't train without an opponent.
鍛錬には相手が必要だ
No matter how hard you try on your own, there are limits.
どんなに自分達だけで頑張ても限界がある
That we were able to regain our connection with Nekoma is a much bigger deal than you or these guys think.
音駒との繋がりを取り戻せたてことは
先生やこいつらが思てるよりずと大きいことなんだ
You did something truly amazing.
あんたはすごいことをやてくれた
What? No, I didn't...
そんないやそんな
If we win tomorrow, then you can praise me all you want.
明日勝てから改めて存分に褒めてくださいよ
I'll make sure to.
確かにな
Okay! Grab your things and head
straight to the gym for a meeting!
おし荷物持てそのまま体育館でミティングすんぞ
Yessir...
You totally drooled again.
お前ヨダレ垂らしてただろきたねぇ
Gross.
My drool isn't gross!
俺のヨダレは汚くねぇ
Oh, they're back!
帰てきた
Congrats on making it to the finals!
決勝進出おめでとう
おお道宮
Oh, Michimiya.
How did you know?
なんで知てんの
They just announced it over the loudspeakers.
さき校内放送で流れて
It's amazing!
すごいよ青城倒して決勝なんてもう
You beat Seijou and made it to the finals! It's just...
Amazing! It's crazy!
すごいよヤバイよ
あんたのボキャブラリがヤバイ
Your lack of vocabulary is crazy.
ていうか顔痣
Wait, what happened to your face?!
Oh, it happened during one of our matches.
今日の試合でちょとな
It looks worse than it is.
見た目派手なだけで大丈夫だよ
I see.
そうなんだ
Hey, boys' volleyball team!
おいバレ男子
すげぇなおい
You guys are amazing!
おめでとう
Congrats!
Hinata! Kageyama! Well done!
日向影山よくやたな
Ma'am!
先生
Thanks!
あざす
I'm gonna cheer you on tomorrow!
明日応援に行くぞ
絶対勝てよ
You better win!
頑張てね
Do your best!
They all stayed after school for us.
皆残てくれてたのか
M-Sta Miyagi is about to start!
「Mスタ宮城」始まちゃう
こんにちばんは
Good after-evening.
Good after-evening!
こんにちばんは
Today, at Sendai City Gymnasium in Tomizawa,
the quarterfinal and semifinal matches were held
本日富沢の仙台市体育館では
全日本バレボル高等学校選手権大会
for the Miyagi prefectural qualifiers of the
National High School Volleyball Tournament,
通称「春高バレ」の宮城県代表決定戦の
準準決勝準決勝が行われました
commonly known as Spring Volleyball Nationals.
Karasuno                                  Aoba Jousai
In the first match, Karasuno High School defeated the powerhouse school Aoba Jousai High School
第１試合は烏野高校が強豪青葉城西高校を破て
to advance to the finals for the first time in years.
久々の決勝進出です
Seijou being eliminated in the semifinals was quite the surprise!
いや驚きましたね
まさか青城がここで姿を消すとは
Indeed.
そうですね
It was a well-balanced team headed by Oikawa,
so it's a shame that we won't see them in the finals.
及川くんをはじめ非常にバランスのよいチムだただけに
決勝でその姿を見られないのは残念です
もうちょと勝た俺たちを映せよ
C'mon! Show us a little more! We actually won!
Yeah, yeah!
そうだそうだ
Stop showing just Seijou!
青城ばか映してんじゃねぇ
This happens every time.
それはいつものことでしょ
They lost in the semifinals. What do you expect?
準決勝だしまあこんなもんだろう
The Champions' Dignity
Semifinals, Round 2
続いては準決勝第２試合
Next, we have the second round of the semifinals.
In this match, the school garnering attention rightfully won and moved on to the finals.
こちらは注目の高校が順当に勝て
決勝に駒を進めたようですよ
Here comes the headliner.
さあ真打の登場だぞ
That would be Shiratorizawa Academy,
the team who won this tournament the last three years.
この大会３年連続優勝
更に今年は１９歳以下の日本代表にも選ばれた
「怪童」牛島若利くん率いる白鳥沢学園です
They're led by Ushijima Wakatoshi,
who has played for the under-19 national team.
Shiratorizawa Academy                                 Kesenuma West High School
準決勝も危なげなくストレトで勝たようですね
Looks like they had no problems winning in straight sets.
Yes.
ええ今年は志願の全国制覇を狙えるメンバが揃いましたからね
They finally have the roster to win nationals, which they have been seeking for years.
I think we can expect great things from them.
期待していいんじゃないでしょうか
地力で勝る白鳥沢学園に対して
It'll be interesting to see how high Karasuno can climb against the powerful Shiratorizawa Academy.
烏野高校がどこまで追いすがるか注目ですね
決勝の模様はご覧のチャンネルで明日午前１１時から生放送です
The final will be broadcast live here at 11:00 AM.
Tomorrow: Volleyball Spring Tournament Finals: Live at 11:00!
Make sure to catch the match that will determine the Miyagi Prefecture representative!
宮城県の頂点を決める一戦ぜひお見逃しなく
Now, tomorrow we'll be going up against Shiratorizawa,
さて明日は白鳥沢と戦うわけだが
but in the three years since Oikawa joined Aoba Jousai,
they've never beaten Shiratorizawa.
これまで及川が入てからの３年間で
青葉城西は一度たりとも白鳥沢に勝たことがねぇ
Not even once.
一度たりともだ
That's why people call them...
人呼んで
undisputed champions.
「絶対王者」
Ushijima is a given, but the rest of the team are some of the best in the prefecture too.
牛島はもちろんだが他にも県でトプクラスのやつらがごろごろいる
県内最強の名は伊達じゃねぇ
It's no fluke that they're the best team in the prefecture.
Shiratorizawa is even better than what you guys are thinking.
白鳥沢はお前らが思てる以上に強ぇ
No one actually thinks we're going to win.
誰も俺たちが勝つなんて思てねぇだろ
Huh?
What is it, Hinata?
何だ日向
None of that matters!
そんなの関係ない
Sir!
と思います
Hey, don't talk to the coach like that!
おいコチに向かてお前
Oh, uh, I didn't mean it like that.
いいえそういう意味じゃなくて
It's fine. Just say it.
いいから言てみろ
R-Right.
誰も俺たちが勝つと思てないのは青城相手でも同じでした
No one thought that we were going to beat Seijou either.
なので関係ないです
That's why it doesn't matter...
Sir.
と思います
We're going to be the challengers again tomorrow.
明日も俺たちは挑戦者だ
Let's turn the tables on them.
大番狂わせ見せてやろうぜ
Yes, sir!
"The fallen champs."
「落ちた強豪」「飛べない烏」
"The clipped crows."
No one will call you that anymore.
君たちをそういうふうに言う者はもうどこにもいません
Those crows are now flying across the great blue sky with the wind under their wings.
いぱいに風を受けた烏が今大空を待ています
And I'm sure that you guys can go anywhere.
そして君たちなら行けるはずです
Higher than anyone,
どこまでも高くどこまでも遠く
and farther than anyone!
All right, everyone. The time has come!
さあ皆さん時は来ました
明日も勝て全国へ行きましょう
Let's win tomorrow and go to nationals!
Yeah!
おしゃあ
Okay. Now get home and go to bed so that you aren't tired tomorrow.
よし疲れ残さないようささと帰てしかり寝ろよ
Yessir!
ウィス
All right, dismissed!
じゃ解散
Yessir!
Kageyama.
影山
Set for me.
トス上げてくれ
Huh? Are they...
まさか
I knew it.
やぱり
Yachi!
谷地さん
Could you throw us some balls?
ボル上げてくれない
You guys played two matches today, so you should go home and rest up.
今日も二試合やたんだしゆくり休んだほうがいいよ
If I went home right now, I'd be too worked up to sleep.
今帰てもムズムズして寝れないんだよ
お願い
So please!
Please!
お願いしゃす
I'm ready!
Okay.
Yeah!
Give me one more!
もう一本頼む
Okay.
One more!
もう一本
Yeah.
What's the matter, Yachi?
どうしたの谷地さん
Oh! I'm sorry!
ごめん
I just remembered something.
なんか思い出しちゃて
What?
何が
二人が喧嘩した時も
The time you two got into that fight, I kept throwing balls to you like this.
ちょうどこんなふうにずとボル上げてたなて
Really?
そうだけ
What?! You don't remember?!
覚えてないの
Hinata, you charged in and grabbed on,
日向が突進して掴みかかたり
and then Kageyama, you threw him on the ground.
影山くんが投げ飛ばして倒したり
I was really scared, you know!
私すごく怖がたんだから
O-Oh...
ななんか
すんません
Sorry.
Oh, uh, I didn't mean it that way.
いやそういうつもりじゃなくて
Watching the matches today got me thinking.
今日の試合見て思たんだ
マネジャにならなかたら
If I hadn't become a manager,
今日の試合見てもこんなにハラハラしたりドキドキしたり
I wouldn't have gotten so worried
or excited watching today's matches.
Nor would I have felt the same passion and joy you guys did from winning.
勝て皆と一緒に喜んだりして
心が熱くなることなかただろうなて
それてずと皆が努力して
It's probably all because I watched each of you work so hard to do something that you couldn't do before.
できなかたことが一つずつできるようになていたのを見てきたから
I never would've had that experience anywhere else.
ここにいなかたらそんなこと絶対なかたから
So thank you!
だから
ありがとう
No, we have you to thank!
そんなこちこそありがとうだよ
You stayed with us through all our practices.
いぱい練習に付き合てくれたし
Without you, we might've never been able to master our new fast attack.
谷地さんいなかたら新しい速攻完成しなかたかもしれないし
Really? A "Townsperson B" like me was able to help?
本当
村人Bの私でも役に立た
Of course!
もちろんだよ東北一の村人Bだよ
You're the best Townsperson B in all of Tohoku!
Is that even a compliment?
お前それ褒めてんのか
Of course it is!
当たり前だろ
お前も感謝してんならちゃんとお礼言えよ
If you're actually thankful too, then say something!
Okay.
Thanks.
あざす
お前それしかねぇのかもと他にいろいろあんだろうが
Is that all?
There's all sorts of other things to say!
Shut up! I thanked her, didn't I?!
うるせぇちゃんと感謝してんだからいいだろうが
I-It's okay...
ままあまあ
何してるの
What are you doing?
し清水先輩
Sh-Shimizu?!
Making sure to rest is another important way to prepare for your next match.
しかり体を休めることも試合に向けての大事な備えだよ
S-Sorry!
すみません
Come on! That's enough!
ほらもう終わり片付けよう
Let's clean up!
What?
早く早く
Come on, hurry up!
Okay...
てめぇのせいで怒られたじゃん
We got in trouble because of you.
You wanted to practice too, didn't you?
お前だて練習したかたんだろ
すみません私も練習に付き合ちゃて
I'm sorry for helping them practice.
No, it's fine.
一緒に練習してくれてありがとうね
Actually, thanks for practicing with them.
Right!
Hitoka, it's already dark out,
so let's go to the bus stop together.
仁花ちゃんもう暗いから一緒にバス停まで行こうか
O-Okay!
Hinata and Kageyama, make sure to head
straight home after you're done cleaning up.
日向と影山は片付けたらすぐ帰ること
Right!
I wonder how the Little Giant felt the day before the finals.
「小さな巨人」は決勝戦の前の日てどんな気持ちだたのかな
I'm super nervous, but...
緊張するけど
isn't it even more exciting now?!
超ワクワクすんな
明日
We're going to win tomorrow.
勝つぞ
Yeah!
We survey the scene while looking at no one in particular
It's fine to be self-satisfied as we stare out from the dark night
And even though there's not a star in the sky, we must reach out our hands
Whether they come for us or not is a different wish of ours
That's right, our breaths and heartbeats can only be found in this world
We're always standing upon a colorless stage
And now we wait in the middle of it for a brand-new sunrise
Though we're at our wit's end and our voices grow hoarse,
we find ourselves
Even in that nameless world,
we keep waiting for a sunrise like the one we saw before
As proof we're living days we can never live again,
we find ourselves
Seriously though, I didn't expect Karasuno to make it all the way to the finals.
いやでもまさか烏野が決勝まで行くとはな
They beat Seijou, so maybe they're becoming a powerhouse again.
青城にも勝たし古豪復活て感じ
Oh, speak of the devil.
噂をすれば
ウシワカだ
It's Ushiwaka.
H-Hey!
日向翔陽
Hinata Shouyou.
Kageyama Tobio.
影山飛雄
決勝まで来ました
We made it to the finals.
コンクリト育ちの俺たちが
We, who grew from the concrete,
あなたをぶ倒して全国へ行きます
will beat you and go to nationals!
楽しみにしている
I look forward to it.
Let's meet on the court.
コトで会おう
Damn it...
I wanna play him right now!
早く戦いてぇ
よし絶対行くぞ春高
All right! We're definitely going to the spring tournament!
しゃあ
Yeah!